Stock about hashing, suppose we want to design a system for storing employee records, kid using phone
numbers, and we want following inquiries to be performed efficiently.
Insert a phone number and corresponding information, search a phone number and fetch the information
and delete the phone number and the related information like this software.
We think about these data structures and the array of phone numbers and records, linkage list of phone
numbers and records.
Balance the tree with phone numbers as key or direct access table.
So these are the data structures that we want to think about them when employing, you know, trying
to implement this software.
With balanced binary search tree, we get moderate search, insert and delete times.
All of this operation can be guaranteed to be all look and done, but we don't need these these complexities.
Another solution that one one can think is to use direct access tape where we can make a big array and
we use a phone number as indexed in the early.
An entity, as in shown in the finger below and entry is array in entry in an array is nil.
A phone number is not present.
Else, the array entry stores pointed to the two records corresponding to phone number.
OK.
These are the actual key, and these are the universal keys.
The key is in green and the data element is green and yellow.
The solution has many practical limitations.
First problem with this solution is extra space required is a huge, for example, a phone number is
and digits.
We need times then and space for table.
Where is the size of the pointer to record this memory limitation?
This complexity, memory complexity will limit us using that direct access tape.
The solution due to the above limitations, direct access stable cannot always be used.
Hashing is the solution that can be used in almost all such situations and perform extremely well compared
to above data structures like array, link and list balanced binary search three in practice.
With hashing, we get all to one search time on average on the reasonable assumptions and all to our
oath and in worst case, consider we have to distinguish between two main concepts that encryption starts
by a plain text with encryption key, it becomes encrypted text while decryption.
We use the same key to make in plain text while hashing.
This encryption used to protect sensitive information while hashing used to validate information plaintext.
Plus, hash function we will see in the next video about the hash functions it becomes.
The hash text we get hash tags.
And we start this is the hashtag, and this is the hashing process.
Hashing is an improvement over direct access tape.
The idea is to use hash function that converts the hash functions.
And this is the key.
Like if I want to store these names John Smith, Lisa Smith and Sandra Dee converse a given phone number.
Or any other key like this to a smaller number and uses the small number as index in the table called
hash table.
We will see the hash function in the next video and let's see how it works and why.